in many of them and in in the Buddhist
writings you often hear about delusion
cre a verion
[Music] delusion Lo do and
delusion Lo do and
MOA
so you know people can get their hea on
Greed to get their head around aversion
but often delusion is kind of regarded
as as something that's not directly my
responsibility in as much as greed is or
aversion I don't know what I don't know
yeah so it kind of it's regarded in sort
of a semi metaphysical sense as in it's
there but it's it's not really something
I can directly
experience uh but actually it is
delusion is an attitude of your mind in
as
much greed or lust and aversion are
otherwise you wouldn't have been
mentioned always like
that so from that point of view delusion
it's more of like um an attitude of indolence indolence
laziness
um choice to keep things cloudy you
exactly keeping it opaque intentionally
not look turning a blind eye distracting
yourself intentionally with things
they're going to take your mind away
from yourself so you realize delusion is a
yourself so you realize delusion is a
very active thing
and as the said that's why it's the most
blame worthy actually because it's the
hardest to undo as
well but the fact that you can undo it
means it's not this metaphysical lack of
knowledge it's your very
attitude that it's even more fundamental
than the attitude of lust and attitude
of aversion they're kind of secondary to
it lust requires a basis of
delusion aversion requires a basis of
delusion delusion requires a basis of
delusion requires a basis of
delusion so you're deluded through and
through not because you don't know
certain things but because you
perpetually act out of ignorance that
then maintains yourself in the situation
of ignorance and situation of ignorance
again it's not ignorance ignorance as in
you don't know something it's you
actively ignoring and giving priority to
the ignoring of
it so choosing choosing to distract
yourself for
example so actively actively um making a
choice that would result in certain
actions that are not necessarily lustful
or
hateful but are are based upon um you
know wanting to be self-aware for
example so
entertainment or dist distraction in
general oh I'm bored by myself because
I'm aware of everything in it's very
unpleasant so I just going to chat to
some people randomly not for sensual
reasons or because I hate them just
because I want something to
do so often needing things to do is
rooted in delusion as in in distraction
as in indolence on the level of like you
can be very diligent externally he's
doing all this work but the reasons for
you doing that work are rooted in you uh
wanting to turn a Blind Eye in regard to
yourself you don't want to be self-aware
basically you don't want to see the
truth of your mind well yeah because
that will result in the unpleasant
truths of your mind or simply unpleasant
states of boredom and so on so I better
find something to do I better find an
external purpose yes that that doing it
will occupy my mind so my mind won't be
aware of itself because being aware of
itself is too unpleasant is too
threatening it's a way of keep covering
up the truth the exactly cover it's it's
the way of uh maintaining yourself in a
state of uh cover up
yeah keep the dust moving exactly
otherwise if it settles you get to see
what's there and it's unpleasant that's
the thing self you say self-aware sounds
like a good thing but it's like the most
painful thing it is yeah you know and
things most people avoid yeah that's why
Solitude is is very unpleasant to begin
with that's why the as the Buddha
himself said many times he practices so
you develop the pleasure of solitude you
develop the pleasure of solitude you
won't get it right away if done rightly
it's unpleasant cuz you're going against the
unpleasant cuz you're going against the
against the grain of all the distraction
you got used to it and that your
existence depends
upon but that's it like when you get
into like when you stop
maintaining all these attitudes of they
were based upon um obscuring the
self-awareness so when you stop feeding
those attitudes the self-awareness
increases but it feels
like the you know the boredom starts
giving rise to dread and anxiety feels
like you yourself are drowning it's
crushing you but what is actually
crushing is your assumed level of your
own being the one that you've been
proliferating it's not actually crushing
you like being alone um in your room not
seeing or talking anyone cannot do
anything to you but yeah your mind can
can sort of drown in it because the mind
became dependent upon a certain degree of
dependent upon a certain degree of
Engagement with the world that is its
threshold but that's not a static thing
that threshold which means the more you
engage the more dependent upon
engagement you
become the less engag well initially it
might hurt the Lesser engagement because
you used to engage more but then you get
used to that and then it will not be
unpleasant in the the same sense like
you have a very hectic person who's been
sort of doing a lot engaging a lot
working a lot for whatever
reasons and then if he was made to sit
down and stop engaging to that
level the discrepancy would be just too
much to
handle but if he gradually starts doing
that and then starts ceasing his
engagement he'll get used to that new
level of of of of um lacking the
engagement that he used to have which
means you are responsible for the
threshold of where your being
is that's why says his Consciousness
gets established upon
that like that becomes the norm that
becomes what you're used to it which
means anything less than that it's going
to fill you with anxiety and
Dread but it's important to recognize
that it's not a static
thing so through through using
engagement with the world
actions meaningless work whatever else
or not not even meaning finding meaning
for your work whatever practically
you're engaging with the world um for
the means of escaping
self-awareness so you will become
dependent on the Lev on that level of
Engagement anything less than that
engagement will bring you back to your
self-awareness so that means then you
have to keep maintaining the level of
your engagement and once you get used to
it you have to keep increasing it if you
try to use it to avoid self-awareness
and most people to a degree are using
that that's why most people are afraid
to be alone Not Afraid from like some
you know monsters and stuff but afraid
just in broad daylight being left alone
in the room for a whole day without
doing anything without taking my mind
away from myself that's why most people
would be afraid to be left
alone it would result in exp anxiety and
existential dread because the human life on average
dread because the human life on average
is about avoiding that self-awareness
which ties in with avoiding
responsibility and feeds one another and
so
on but that self-awareness is the thing
that's going to make things right anyway
exactly that's why people are because of
their own
actions they're liable to suffering
because of that not because of some
someone else's fault or or or some
design it's because you act in a manner that
it's because you act in a manner that
keeps making you liable to suffer keep
keeps you
exposed so you could
then if you take responsibility for it
that's where what I'm saying might
become apparent that the level of Engagement
apparent that the level of Engagement
the level of distraction the level of
turning a blind eye it's not a static
thing which means you can the way you've
been kind of proliferating it you can
then also undo it if you stop engaging
with it or you can suddenly put a brakes on
it or you can suddenly put a brakes on
its its
growth that's why the Bava in the Sut is
being again it's not a metaphysical
thing it's it's the level of your
dependence on the senses which is
Central being the level of dependence on the
being the level of dependence on the
sense of of of um of the world the duty
the the perception thing you perceive
around the level you depend on it
but then you can start depending
less that's why arahan has sensation of
his being he doesn't depend on
anything but he's still there it's not
that the being means destruction no
being means
assumption Assumption of Engagement
Assumption of avoiding responsibility
Assumption of
sensuality and that's what illusion is
that ignoring turning a blind eye
distracting yourself not being able to
live with
yourself and again you can ask back onto
that practical level that we always do
why is
it that I don't want to be
self-aware why is it that I need to
distract myself from
myself because it's
unpleasant so why am I then maintaining
this whole level of being for which I'm
responsible level of how much I depend
on engagement with them things oh it's
cuz I don't want to
suffer but failing to see that my very
engagement is is the root of your
suffering exactly yeah so why do I
suffer then oh it's because I keep
running away from suffering that's why I
suffer so if I stop running away from
suffering I at least have a chance to
not suffer